[Music]
John's real pleasure Tufts at a MIDI
it's a pleasure to sit down with you
David it's nice to meet you in person
yeah feels strange because we've spoken
quite a few times online mm-hmm and I've
office leaving following a lot of your
work and especially the kind of journey
that you've been on so a wait for people
who don't know I think most people who
watch the channel will kind of already
be familiar with your work but awakening
from the meaning crisis is now 40 42
episodes 42 episodes maybe 43 or 44 by
the time this comes out yeah probably
yes yeah but what I find what I'm really
looking forward to exploring in this
conversation is what comes next because
I know that you've got some really
exciting and interesting ideas for what
is going to happen next I think so
but also what the journey has been like
and I'm reminded of a mutual friend of
both of ours Peter Limburg talks about
this kind of sending out mimetic
artifacts into the world and seeing what
comes back so we're sort of putting up a
flag we're putting our stuff out in
YouTube we don't know if anyone's going
to watch it we don't know if it's going
to resonate with anyone and then often
it does and I think would you say that
your work has resonated as well as you
had hoped or expected or that's a that's
a tricky question I'd hoped it resonated
because and I had some reason to believe
it would in some ways because of the
response to you know that material in in
classrooms and I had an earlier version
you know Buddhism in Karzai that course
and you know there was and that that had
it had gotten a response beyond sort of
what I had expected but it's been more
than I've expected it's it's it it's I
don't know what to say it's a little bit
intimidating at times
I'll get you know I'll get email about
people who are doing meetups and
watching this series literally from all
around the world and that's been both
very exciting and
also a little bit like challenging
because you know I think seriously my
responsibility to my students and I'm
not quick I'm sort of working out in my
mind what's what is my what are my
responsibilities now like for example
just to give you a practical example I
can't respond to every comment that
comes at every video that would be the
last I that would fill my days and I
can't do that so but you know Newt I
can't I don't want to just ignore
comments so I'm I'm very much in the
process of trying to figure out what
what what can I with integrity do that
you know is satisfying the
responsibilities I should have two
people who are devoting I understand
this they're devoting often considerable
time and attention to trying to follow
the work I'm putting out so that's
something that's very much a work in
progress for me right now for people
maybe you haven't been sort of following
it closely what's the overall frame
what's the elevator pitch for awakening
from the meaning crisis so the elevator
pitch for awakening from the meeting
crisis is the idea bringing together two
sort of strands one is an idea that that
human beings face perennial problems
with their existence because of the
centrality to their existence of their
ability to make meaning so at the core
of our cognition or our ability to make
meaning it's central to communication
problem solving I would argue
intelligence consciousness etc and then
one of the main ideas is the very
processes that makes our intelligence
and that meaning making so adaptive also
makes us perennially susceptible to self
deceptive self-destructive behavior so
cultures across historical contexts
environmental contexts have generally
put together sets of practices for
intervening and helping to ameliorate
some of these perennial problems of
self-deceptive self-destructive behavior
and then what you need in addition to
that is you need that though that set of
practices to be home within a world view
that legitimates them valorizes sets up
traditions sets up institutions that's
communities sets up exemplars all that
paradigmatic work so that people know
how to understand and judge and evaluate
and pursue the cultivation of wisdom and
what I mean by wisdom is exactly those
set of practices that help us to address
the the the problems of self-deception
the problem that's happened for us is
that the worldview within which our
wisdom traditions arose has been
significantly undermined for a host of
very interconnected and complex
historical reasons that have to do with
things like the Protestant Reformation
the emergence of the scientific
worldview the movements in the
separation of philosophy from a
transformative set of practices unlike
what it was in the ancient world with
Socrates or Plato we get the loss of
wisdom institutions like the monastic
tradition within the West is destroyed
because of the Protestant Reformation so
for a whole host of historical reasons
we have a worldview in which we as
meaning makers don't belong and then we
also and that worldview also doesn't
tell it tells us how to get information
and even if right even if you if you
want to give sort of a broad reading
side to tell us how to get knowledge but
it really doesn't tell us how to
cultivate wisdom again not meaning just
some lofty ideal it's like no no it's
you know how things how these problems
sink their teeth into people's lives and
shred them and and and so what's
happening is we don't have a worldview
that homes even educates guides there's
none of that paradigmatic homing for
these practices and so people are bereft
they don't know where to go for wisdom
they pursue it often in an autodidactic
matter they write they form sort of
pseudo religious responses to try and do
the work that has been lost and so I
won't get into all of the symptom ology
but there's all of these different
things that you can see happening that
are response to this so what the series
is is a
a historical analysis of how we lost
that valorising worldview and that a
cognitive scientific analysis about what
is the meaning making machinery
what is self-deception what are higher
states of consciousness what is
enlightenment what is wisdom what's our
best cognitive scientific answer that
and then can we use that to create what
I call psycho technologies and
communities and ecologies of them that
can give us back the cultivation of
wisdom and self transcendence and also
connect us up to a world of you that
valorizes homes legitimates and make
sense of that set of practices so that's
what the series is all about and I guess
just tying together that and the idea of
supporting putting this out as a kind of
memetic transmission I know you've
connected with other people who are
asking those kind of questions and what
do you sense the answers might be where
do you sense that are there projects in
the works or are there people who are
thinking about these and where do you
think this conversation goes now yeah
there's a lot and and and what's
interesting and this was this was a
aspect of the mimetic artifact that was
unexpected and so I often refer to it as
a gift the fact that I've been put into
contact with so many people who are
putting as I'd like to say really real
time and talent and often their their
personal finances into trying to create
ecologies of practices and communities
to home those practices and to provide a
place of paradigmatic you know guidance
so I you know I'm talking I'm regularly
talking to people like Rafe Kelly and
you know he's he just has done a retreat
and I'm gonna be also talking to some of
his students what I want and he's
putting to get you know he's trying to
get movement practices like you know
people who are like so he's got
expertise in parkour and he teaches
people how to go out and do parkour in
nature and then move that was integrate
there were some mindfulness practices
and then integrate that with some
meditative practices and then you've got
something like a circling practice you
sit around a camp
fire and then you talk and literally
it's like a primordial you know campfire
and you talk and but he also has
lectures where he then tries to
integrate some of the cognitive science
and some of the history from the series
explicitly into all of this and so you
know I'm talking with him and he's put
he just put out an online course now or
he's trying to make it available for
people in general or I'm talking to Mike
man he runs a dojo and he wants he's
trying to put together we meeting
regularity and he's trying to put tear
tear of the curriculum and he says I
want to take this to adolescence I get
these kids coming into the dojo and so
he does martial arts like in the
comprehensive sense it's not just a
self-defense it's a philosophy a'right
it's a way of cultivating wisdom and he
says I want to put together a curriculum
a course I want to take their stuff
you're doing John which is you know
admittedly often very abstract and how
do we put it in two sets of lectures
practices exercises for these kids so
doing things like that or I get to meet
right I get to well it's been on your
channel I get to meet people like Jordan
Hall and I you know and Internet into
this you know you know Reagan we've
we've become friends and entering like
into these regular discussions about ok
what what he talks about you know game
be and I talk about trying to break out
of the cultural cognitive grammar we
have and get a new one and like what
okay let's stop I'm never gonna stop
theorizing because I'm a scientist but
not let's not just theorizing and let's
what does it look like to try and do
that and so I've also met guys and stalk
the guy who invented circling right and
so we are we're regularly getting
together and and and and this is also
because of you mentioned in Peter
Lindbergh right it's like okay can we
take these new emergent psycho tech and
I am really interested in guy's work
because and this is the thing that's
very interested me is because guy has
made it very clear and he and I we're in
pretty much daily communication about
you know the deep hi daguerreian
foundations the deep existential
foundations of circling and so that's
because I think I see if Heidegger is
one of them
prophets of the meaning crisis and the
problem of nihilism so there's somebody
taking Heidegger and Heidegger is not an
easy to read like you know you don't
take Heidegger to the beach right
and yet he's taking this very you know
hired Heidegger is filled with
neologisms and difficult often turgid
prose and guys Trent has been
translating that you know for decades
now into this very successful practice
for changing dialogue and discourse so
you know and so we're all talking
together and also my colleague and
co-author Christopher master Piero so
we're getting together and it's very
much this participant observation can we
start to you like three is that the
right word I don't want to say
re-engineer maybe it's just engineer you
know a as you know psycho technologies
of communication they can and this is
something that I see emerging it's on
rebel wisdom you know the whole
collective intelligence thing what's the
psyche what is the psycho technology or
maybe I think a better term for that is
Jordans term Jordan Hall's term what's
the matter sico technology that will tap
into the collective intelligence of
distributed cognition and give us a
what's the word a resource by which we
can vet was really which we can Shepherd
by which we coordinate all these
emerging and ancient psycho technologies
of wisdom practice so that we can create
something that's alive that that you
know that is self-organizing and
self-correcting and self-transcending
and can evolve with the rapidly changing
nature of our increasingly complex
defying society so that's all what's
really going on right now and it's
taking up a lot of my time and but
that's not a complaint I was surprised
by how much I well I was saying to my
son the other day is like this has
become a job like it like I like a thank
you and so I mean part of what I'm
trying to figure out personally is how
do i integrate that with my job as you
know as as a professor at the University
of Toronto but that's it that's an
interesting problem to have just to sort
of zoom out a little bit a lot of this
is in I think that the kind of cultural
context that we're looking at
and certainly that I'm looking at all
that I'm bringing to it is this sense of
the new atheist hegemony certainly
culturally that I was aware of in the
media and in the sort of wider yeah and
the wider media landscape was sort of
Richard Dawkins Sam Harris scientific
rationalism and that seems to have been
kind of broken and we're now in a place
and I know that a lot of the people that
we've had on our channel and that you've
been talking to as well are looking at
what the function that religions used to
fill and what now can go in that into
that whole yeah what I mean that that's
the big question at the moment I think
isn't it I think so I mean I I tread
that I think this is the ground that
needs to be tread but I tread it very
very carefully because well I mean part
of the part of the people and talking to
and that and I'm better fitting
immensely from the conversations are
like people like Paul van der clay and
Jonathan pazzo he's both of them have
been on your channel and because I see
them I mean Jonathan I think
independently came to hit something very
similar about zombies as you know a
mythic representation of the mean crisis
and he and I have been in conversation
and you know and his work on symbolism I
think is it is part of what you're
talking about like trying to understand
the functionality of symbolism and
that's something that I do some work on
and so I I do think hmm I do think that
what's needed is again I want to be very
careful here I don't want to be
dismissive
I don't want to claim here's what I
don't want to come I don't want to claim
that people in Christianity can't make
Christianity work as a place where they
can tap into the traditions tap into an
ecology and cultivate wisdom and
compassion I think that would be a false
claim so I'm not trying to make that
claim but what I would say is I I'm I
have suspicions I don't have conclusions
but I have suspicions that with the
demise of what I call the axial age that
two worlds mythology as a way of trying
to
understand to articulate processes of
self-transcendence and wisdom
cultivation as that two worlds mythology
has collapsed under the weight of
history and mythology meaning the divine
and yes now Gerald and so the ideal
world we've collapsed one into the
scientific rationalist one yes there's
one land base yeah yeah so so if you if
you think about what Charles Taylor's
talked about in the axial age we have
the great dis embedding there was there
was sort of a unified integrated cosmos
and we're in which there wasn't any sort
of difference in degree between the
Devon there's a tremendous difference in
power but there isn't difference in kind
between sort of the divine realm and the
human or there's cut so it's it's not
paradoxical for the Pharaoh to be a God
or for perc Uli's to become you know to
ascend into God like you know there's
but and what happens is I argue that
that's because what's what's going on
there is this right what it is is a
different understanding of wisdom than
the one we have that it's a pre axial
understanding in which the point of
wisdom is to is to pick up on these
these cycles and and this continuum and
fit into it very well but with it with
the advent of a lot of psycho
technologies like alphabetic literacy
and numeracy and and other things like
that people get a sort of metacognition
is your awareness of your own cognition
they get it and they get an enhanced
metacognitive awareness of of well of
the water was mentioned in earlier of
the self-deceptive aspects of their own
cognition and and then and then you get
you get this sort of double awareness
our cognition is really beset by
self-deception but it's also really
capable of self transcendence because
those two are inter penetrating you
can't have one without the other right
and so the way to try and articulate
that myth that mythologically is well
there's a lower world in which were sort
of encased in the illusion or the
decadence and then there's a other
better world where where where things
really are and we're we where we can
really be and that the point of wisdom
is not
into this world down here but to somehow
ass and right and you and there's all
kinds of variations on that and I see I
see a look and many of the world
religions were born in that axial period
and you know and that's the heritage
from which Christianity emerges and I
see I see Christianity is still embedded
with that fundamental grammar that's got
sort of solidified into the natural and
the supernatural and things like that
which is why you don't think like
Jonathan and Paul that Christianity can
be the vehicle because they effectively
want to see Christianity kind of
rebooted yeah but you think that we've
lost that grammar fundamentally so we
need something different is that yeah I
mean that's that's the gist of my
argument now I am being tentative about
that I didn't say that I don't think I
don't think that I don't I wouldn't
regard that as a conclusive argument I
have suspicions that right that like I
you know I I want to say I'm impressed
by what they're doing and I want to keep
watching and I want to keep talking to
them and I want I don't want to
foreclose and say no it's impossible so
I'm not saying that but what I say is I
suspect that we're the Christianity is
so bound to that grammar that as that
grammar is being destroyed by these
historical you know forces the history
of philosophy the advent of science
right all of these things that have
reinvented us back into our bodies back
into the physical world back into
biological history
like where's deep lyrium bedded now and
so I suspect that why many people are
leaving and the nuns NO NES no organized
religion is an increasingly growing it's
not been growing but the rate at which
is growing is growing right you know
it's an it's it's getting larger and
larger demographic group and it's going
to become the dominant group in the
society right so I what I'm surmising is
for many people the the the organized
religions because of the way they're
bound to a grammar that just doesn't
jive that that's not an option for them
but as you said and this is Nietzsche's
point of the madmen in the marketplace
you can't like just like trying to just
oh well no more God right right the that
the tremendous functionality that
because what religion did and this is
one of Paul's great point right is it is
religion does the kind of thing we're
talking about here it gives this
comprehensive ecology and tradition and
dynamic self create correcting not
perfectly self directing but what is you
know this process forgiving people you
know all of these psycho technologies of
self transcendence and the cultivating
of wisdom and it did it in a way that
was scaleable like for you know all
aspects of society right and you know
and you know also developmentally
scalable you could teach it to adults
and you can teach it to children and
like and so it gave you this
comprehensive way of intervening in
people's consciousness and their
cognition right and their character
right and so you can just sort of oh
well like just leave that space empty
and so what I argue is the attempts we
made to replace that in the 20th century
with totalitarian ideologies what will
create is our systems of ideas that
totally will get that sort of totality
of intervention but if they didn't give
totality of an intervention one of my
critiques is the these ideologies don't
give people sets of practices other than
political engagement or revolution or
things like that so the totalizing was
just a totalization of belief and
control it wasn't actually giving what I
would call like a comprehensive set of
interventions so the the pseudo
religious totalitarian ideologies
drenched the world in Titanic blood
because they they kept promising that
right the secular equivalent of the
other world the upper world the
supernatural world the the promised land
the forthcoming paradise and not and but
they couldn't actually deliver it
because they couldn't actually promote
the kind of transformation that I think
is needed for addressing the perennial
problems so
they get violent because I think there
was sort of frustration built into the
heart of their machinery and they
drenched the world in blood and they
drenched the world and led to a carport
wrong we're caught we're caught between
for many of us I don't want to say all
of us I'm trying to I'm trying to be
very respectful here but for many of us
increasingly so then the nostalgic
return to the existing religions is not
an option the pseudo religious political
ideologies are not an option
and so almost in a Jungian sense were
stuck and so the idea is well we need we
need something like we need something
that's got the comprehensiveness the
scalability of religion without right
pinning us back into its it's code that
doesn't work in many ways or become the
I give a purely sort of political
socio-political or SATs surrogate for
that so that's what I call the religion
of not religion and this is the this is
the the work that this is an aspect of
my work that both Jordan Hall and guys
sent stock are very very interested in I
think people like Paula and Jonathan are
interested in it and I know they are
because there's people in their audience
that are commenting on this like Mary
Cohen and others and they're very
interested in it because they do take I
ultimately they're going to disagree
with it of course but I they do think
that this idea about getting really
clear about the functionality of
religion and that that's got to play an
important part and responding to the
meaning Krista they take that very
seriously of which I'm very appreciative
yeah so this is really really focus on
practice and I know that this is sort of
where you're now turning your energy to
at the end of the awakening from the
meaning crisis like you're focusing very
clearly on practice and the the in
particular dialogic practices very much
very much so yeah so what I what what
I'm doing is the follow-up series is
called after Socrates the pursuit of
wisdom through authentic dialogue and
the idea behind this is and this was an
idea that I
that was sparked in dialogue with Jordan
Hall so it's exemplifying the very thing
I'm trying to get a grip on which Jordan
and I were talking I think was on one of
the ones that's recorded for rebel
wisdom and I'm trying to understand his
notion of coherence because he's he uses
it to extend all right and I'm trying to
okay I get that and he and I'm trying to
say but like can we create some sort of
bridging term between that notion and
what I'm talking about because I know
he's very interested and I'm grateful
for that very supportive of a lot of the
vocabulary and the grammar that I've
been introducing and so he said well
this is it and he had one of those one
of his moments the Jordanian moments
where he does the that thing that's so
wonderful and he said what I'm talking
about with coherence is a meta psycho
technology and he said you know and it's
a meta psycho technology because that
will help to sort of Shepherd right you
know an ecology of psycho technologies
because I talked about that what part of
the functionality of what religions did
is they gave us and I'm using the word
ecology is a very strong analogy right
the the individual components are
adopting self-organizing like organisms
but they're also shaping a collective
environment in a collective space in
which there are checks and balances on
the whole system so that's what I mean
by an ecology and he says but you need
something that sort of Shepherds that
because you're gonna need to dispense
with obsolete ones you're gonna need to
engineer new ones you know and you're
gonna need to you know reorient them and
and he said so you're gonna need a meta
cyclic technology and I went oh my gosh
yes and then it in my mind was ringing
the idea well you know you need this
meta psycho technology for tapping into
activating an accessing and accelerating
and exacting you know the collective
intelligence of distributed cognition
but that needs to be coordinated with
that needs to be coordinated with the
meta heuristic of wisdom which I'm
talking a lot about right now and
remind me I'd like to come back to that
issue about you know sort of a broader
notion of rationality of wisdom in in
the post new atheist world because I
think that's an important part of this
but so you've got and I thought okay so
that and soon as I put those two
together in my mind
Jordan's notion of the meta site with
technology and and what and there and
you know there's the term from the
Berlin paradigm some of the cognitive
scientists who do work on wisdom about
wisdom as they met a heuristic I thought
oh that we had that in the ancient world
we had that in the ancient world and
what we what we had and you can see it
in exemplified in Socrates and in the
Platonic dialogues is we had dialectic
don't hear that don't hear that don't
hear that through the Galleon ears
there's a what I want to talk about is
something that's in some sense a
precursor to Hegel's dialectic but it's
much more as you said and this is
crucially the difference it's much more
about practice it's not about a sort of
logic for understanding world history
and translating that into political
activism that's not what I'm talking
about so what'd you get what'd you have
in dialectic right which comes out of
Socratic and Lanka's because you've got
this process by which these and I'm like
I said I'm trying to I'm in the midst of
doing this it's so I'm talking to people
and I'm doing a lot of participant
observation on one hand and then doing a
lot of research into you know dance
Berbers work on the on how reason is
probably ultimately dialogical in nature
or how the way metacognition actually
works etc so but here are the dimensions
so if you look at sort of dialectic it's
it develops especially into the
Neoplatonic tradition there's like a
horizontal dimension which is what you
guys are exploring it's like what
happens when we get people and instead
of what Plato would call Philae and IKEA
the pursuit of victory they're actually
doing finally of Sofia what they want to
do is they want to access the logos they
want to generate some emerge
system between them that can tap into
your term collective intelligence of
distributed cognition and take that take
us to places that we can't get to on our
own and then what's going on right if
you've got all those dimensions is
you're getting something like a flow a
flow state in which all those dimensions
are being optimized and coordinated when
it's working and so I'm trying to
understand what other dimensions how are
they working and what I want to do is I
want to get that I'm like I'm I'm I'm
trying to do a historical and causing a
scientific analysis of what was going on
and in the ancient dialectic and then
put it into dialogue and that is not a
pond I mean that put it as a dialogue
with all of these practices that are
trying to access collective intelligence
and I'm trying to learn them from the
inside as much as I can and see if we
can engineer something that would do
something like something like you know
take circling and bring it bring into it
something like Philae or Sofia like you
see in the Platonic dialogues
yeah we're circling but what the point
of the circling is not just the dialogue
itself not just the community it's also
yeah but let's turn that what is wisdom
what is it what is it well you know what
is courage what is it what is meaning
like bring it in to do that right and
and and and and so wait and so bring in
like the circling bring in aspects of
what I would call far lia sophia bring
in some of you know what you know what
peter lindbergh talked about when you
talked about the anti debate about
trying to re craft argumentation so
we're not pursuing Philae and okiya the
love of victory but so that we we can
you know we can afford this collective
flow that generates this emergent
dynamical system the logos that can be a
place from which we can draw powerful
insights so that we can start to get you
know we don't have a good adjective here
there I want to say practical but that's
not the right word but we can get really
existentially transformative
practical advice and guidance on how to
make psycho technologies how to Shepherd
them everything that Jordan was
proposing with the meta circuit
technology that's what I want to do with
this series the first half will be
episodes on that historical calling
scientific analysis of dialectic the
second half will be you know you know
you know talking to people interviewing
participant observation reporting on all
of these emerging practices hmm
how urgent a project he feeling that
this this is at the moment well there's
two senses within which it's urgent one
I think is as Kairos and I hear so many
people on your channel talking about
that and I take that very seriously III
agree with that I there's a sense of a
Kairos here there's a sense of a turning
and and and there's a sense almost like
in the biblical sense of death we've got
it we've got to get our sensibilities
really finely attuned to this turning so
that we don't screw it up and we get it
right right and and so I think that's
why this project is very urgent for me
because I want to try and help that
turning right but there's also this the
urgency I take very seriously you know
the fact that a lot of the things that
are distressing a lot of the things that
have been indicated as markers of
general systems collapse and
civilization collapse or seem to be
accelerating you know we have I think we
have just incontrovertible and a
incontrovertible evidence of ecological
degradation which is what you see when
civilizations are you know close
we definitely have we have political
ossification stagnation and inability
for institutions to solve our problems
we have you know we have a breakdown of
a shared worldview we have lots of
indications that people are suffering
existential and mental strain in ways
that are accelerating a lot of stuff I
talked about in in the symptomology of
the meeting crisis and that's all
happening when we're we seem to in by
many and this is you know Steven
Pinker's thing by many of the measures
we've seemed we should be
he seems to be sort of sort of like why
aren't you just why are you just
enjoying that where this is the golden
time we've never eradicated so much
poverty in the world and reduce so much
violence and but that's also a marker of
a civilization that's about to tip and
so all of these things you know maybe
I'm wrong maybe he's right maybe the his
graphs will continue to go right but I
don't think I don't think I like part of
the thing that I've seen is just the
like I you know Jordan Peterson and my
work touched a nerve and other people's
work there's a you know about the
meaning quite touched a nerve I have so
many people that write in and say you're
you're you're putting into words what
I've been going through for years and
right and they don't necessarily think
you know agree with my salute my
response or anything but it's just that
that there was something going on there
the same thing I was I was at a live Q&A
a couple days ago and people are coming
up and yeah you know you have to take
this properly but people are saying you
know you sort of saved my life or
something I think I don't want to
dismiss that I you don't want to you
don't want to go the wrong way with it
either but what they're trying what I
believe they're trying to say is this
hat this is an urgent thing in my life
and a life and a lot in the lives of a
lot of people around me and you know
you're bringing it to articulation in a
powerful so for you know I think I pay
attention to all these signs and I pay
both the positive and the negative and
like I say the video that Chris and I
did on the symptom ology the meaning
crisis we lay out that argument I take
that all very seriously and I take the
response that I'm getting to my work and
to and related work I think that all
very seriously so not only do I sense
there's a Kairos that we got to get
right I think there's a threat that's
imminent and if we don't do something
about it we're going to be overtaken by
it given that sort of perspective why do
you think that this con this particular
piece about dialogue is the key response
to that if we're if we are threatened
why is that the right focus so I I want
to be careful I'm not claiming it's any
kind of excuse
thing to do my my way of doing a
explaining why I think it's how it could
play an important role is that I think
that we have overwhelming historical and
increasingly scientific evidence that
people will undergo the significant
transformations that are needed in order
to address major threats like this right
they will take serious hits to their
standards of living they will take they
they'll dildo they're willing to undergo
sort of significant political and
socio-economic experiment if they see
lots of meaning making is going to come
out of it but if they're in a meaning
famine and they're in there in a
scarcity mentality of meaning they also
fire they lose they lose cognitive
flexibility they lose the capacity for
insight they lose the capacity for
aspiration and transformation and right
and and then they they they become in a
very important sense rigid and and then
they cling on to the other things that
they would sacrifice if meaning was more
apparent so if and I and yet and you and
I've been talking about this we don't
mean meaning like in the Hallmark card
oh that's a wonderful meaning we mean
you know actual practices that will go
into people's lives and give them
responses to the perennial problems and
facilitate them you know increasing
their sense of connectedness to
themselves to each other in the world
that's what I mean when I say meaning
and if we can give that to people I
think then people are willing to go
through that that the changes and the
sacrifices that are going to be needed
to address these other problems but
that's again why we need the religion of
no religion we need this can't be done
on an individual ad hoc basis that's why
this the the collect the the the the
collective intelligence is where we're
going to create as the religion of no
religion that gives people this meaning
right and gives them the functionality
that will do that comprehensive
transformation of consciousness
cognition character and communitas that
we're going to need if we're going to
solve to address these issues so I don't
think of it as I wouldn't say like it's
the sole locus but I think if we don't
get it if we don't address this then
people people will not have the needed
cognitive and existential resources to
do what's going to be needed like I see
it in my son's my older sons friends
it's like they know that their standard
of living isn't going to be right and
they and they see and they're we they
are really worried that their that the
world is dying and and right and they
get all that but yet they're like but
they they're they're I don't want to be
insulting but they're kind of fragile
because they don't have they don't for
lack of a better word they don't have a
depth of wisdom right so their lives are
already so caught up with these
unaddressed perennial problems that they
have very little left over to address
these looming existential threats that
they can't avoid acknowledging and so
they're they're often fragile and I
really really feel for them in a
profound way yeah I find that the focus
on transformative conversation to be
really really exciting and it's what so
from the beginning of rebel wisdom I was
sort of following like initially the
focus on Jordan Pederson and we've
talked about this before the eye but
Jordan Peterson for me at his best with
his lectures there's a kind of sense of
exploration and there's almost this
sense of a dialogue with him with the
audience even though it's a monologue he
sort of you don't know where he's going
to go and there's an emergent quality to
a lot of what he's saying and then a
sense with the intellectual dark web
when it was first announced and framed
was around oh these are people who are
going to have a conversation they might
change their minds there's an aliveness
and there was some of that in some of
the talks but that was not really borne
out like I don't think we've had a
public example of what that
a transformative conversation really
looks like where we go in and
potentially change our minds but how can
people have these kind of genuinely
transformative conversations I think
once you get a certain profile and you
get identified with a certain position
it's much harder to do that for example
the new atheist position and sam harris
but but this is where i think a lot of
our attention has gone to it's like what
does a transformative conversation look
like how do we do it and how can we get
ourselves into that space because
without it I don't think we're going to
get to the truth I totally agree with
that
and and part of it for me is is that III
would say it's something more than just
a transformative conversation that
that's what I'm trying to get at
dialectic is bringing in sort of a bunch
of different transformative psycho tech
we're conversation is one of them but
they're being coordinated in a way and
so I'm really interested in that because
I one of the things I argue in the
series is that the the we've got to get
below propositional knowing to the
procedural and the perspectival and in
the participatory if we're going to
actually get people to transform in the
way they need to in order to meet what
Thomas Bjorkman calls the meta crisis so
I agree with all of that I get and part
of what I part of what I'm excited about
well I'm excited about the fact that you
know like it sorry it was recent and it
had just a Titanic impact on all of us
like those like there was a four-way
thing between guy and Jordan and
Christopher master Pietro and myself we
recorded it and we all came away from
that saying da da like Jordan said he
was ringing and he had to have an app
and guy was just saying he said you know
I hope I never recover from that
conversation what an amazingly beautiful
thing to say I hope I never recover from
that conversation and I just came I came
I had to do I was supposed to be doing
work after that I couldn't I was I was
pacing around my apartment I was like oh
right because it was we were not only
talking because I had framed the
conversation I want to talk about this
project of dialectic but I felt that at
many points in that that dialogue we
actually were exemplifying that what I'm
talking about and and and if and and and
and and it goes to the core of your
thing what we law you know when we move
from the platonic dialogue to the
Aristotelian monologue we lost something
and I'm very well well of that I'm
really well aware of that temptation I'm
a professor I get to stand up and do the
monologue and I'm doing it in this
series but there was no monologue there
at all like and you know and and the way
like what was happening there they it
was it in my opinion it's the logos
there's this joint supervening
authorship that you're participating in
you know it's just possibly receiving
but you're not make that's it's that
it's it's participatory and transfer
transformative in the participation and
so just that for me was proof of concept
that for me was proof of concept that
this kind of thing is possible we can
move from a monologue to a dialogue and
the dialogue can be doing work like it's
not just right and and it's fair to say
this because guys responsive to this he
I said like I understand what circling
does for people on its own and I belong
to a circling group now and I value it
but but it I want we need dialectic yeah
I agree I think I think I I find it a
bit repetitive film on YouTube I find a
bit repetitive to just keep going back
to okay the nature of the present moment
it's like okay that's fine but where's
the content where's the like that that's
something we're really exploring as well
at the moment with we're about to
announce a whole we've done a collective
intelligent series we're about to
announce an event where we're going to
call it impossible conversations and
we're going to use sort of serve the
circling modality and then introduce hot
topics hot cultural topics into it and
then take people into like discussing
gender or kind of
of immigration or whatever a topic that
often will get heated and then ask
people to come out of that again like
almost like stop come out and now talk
about like what I came up what happened
so starting to get a kind of almost
object relation to our own belief
structures realizing okay I realize like
I'm holding that here I got much more
upset than I expect it to be or whatever
excellent so that that's where it sounds
very similar to what I'm talking about
very similar indeed introducing content
to the kind of the we space practices I
suppose yes introducing content but also
yeah well as long as we explain what we
mean by content I'm not I'm not
interested in just generating more
propositions I'm generating I have
interests in generating insight right so
that like again this why the template of
the Socratic dialogues is so important
to me and very often those dialogues
will end what's really important that
the work of like you know Gonzalez on
this or especially Sarah rapid his book
on this or Moore's book on there's this
Renaissance of all this happening right
the dialogues will often end went out
with aporia like you know I think it's
the lysis where it's you know what's
courage and you know he's and we all go
to war all through this and it ends and
nobody and you and if you just look at
the propositions that look like well
that was a waste of time but what
happens at the end of the day you have
to read get to pay attention to the
drama because the drama is where play
that's what Plato is using to try and
point to the collective intelligence
because what happens in the drama is
both the interlocutors with Socrates say
we want we want our sons to come in and
spend time with you and learned courage
from you and you think what what what
what happened because Socrates wasn't
able to produce a definition of courage
and what you do and this is drew
Highlands point no home you go back and
look what Socrates was doing
he's exemplifying something that can't
be captured in a definition and so the
self-awareness and the self-knowledge
isn't just about well what are we doing
right now in the present moment it's
like oh look what we can do by coming
into the present moment is we can
discover
how we're exemplifying the thing we're
trying to understand and that can give
us a kind of deep participatory
transformative insight into what it is
and that's where the recursive ad of
things like circling can become the self
awareness of exemplification that's the
kind of thing I see as a real puzzle and
that's what was happening in that
four-way discussion we were going we
would step back and we'd say something
like you know what's going on in
vulnerability and what I say okay but I
remember at one point I said okay but if
we're trying to understand this like
visit can we is there a way in which the
world is vulnerable because like an
indictment guy literally sort of shifted
around in his chair and he oh because it
was like we're exemplifying this but
what does it mean let's not just note it
but what does it tell us about our
attempts to connect to the world about
the phenomenology of our ontology what
does it tell us right now we've got
we've got a moment here we've got a
moment
that's where instead of just noting
right and we can we can we can actually
do something like what was going on in
dialectic so you mentioned before that
we might come back to rationality of
wisdom yeah yeah so this is this is part
of my response to what you mentioned
about the the loss of the hegemony of
the New Atheists and part of and this is
actually the series of videos that are
coming out right now though the section
on sort of rationality and wisdom and
part of part of my critique of the new
atheist is I think they have a very thin
and truncated notion of rationality and
I'm trying to get back to a notion of
rationality that is clearly related as
it was in the ancient world to wisdom we
should be cultivating our best wisdom
and rationality as we come into these
dialogues and then those dialogues
should be feeding back into taking us
beyond where we can go on our own which
is central to cultivate the cultivation
of wisdom so I think those two that's
part of what I want to talk about
because
again what I mean by dialectic it's not
that's why and sometimes I try to get a
term I'm sort of playing with the
neologism of just using the the ancient
Greek as something that's beyond
dialogue and dialectic like sometimes
called a diya logos to emphasize the
generation of the logos and the logos is
both something like I said that's in the
meta psycho technology but also
something that I then internalize as I
as I cultivate wisdom and the two are
just well they're they're feeding into
each other so the new series after
Socrates what do you hope to achieve
through it
do you gee I guess it sounds to me like
you want to be kind of going on a bit of
a journey yes during it where do you
hope to be at the end of the twenty
episodes so I one of my the Keystone's
of my pedagogy is to put myself on to a
journey of learning and then share that
as opposed to just disseminating
information and so that's where I think
my best teaching happens and I'm hoping
and this is not again this is something
that this is something I'm aspiring to
in Agnes coloured sense that I will be
in the sense of I'm going to be a
different person at the end of this and
I'm hoping that dialectic and the way
I've tried to explain it will be so
first of all personally will be as
central to my own spirituality for lack
of a better word I don't like that word
but that you know meditation is
contemplation is Tai Chi Chuan is Alexio
Devine is and there's an important
that's going to be part of this area
there's an important thing between Lexi
Oh Davina as a style of reading and
dialectic that's also Oh Lexi Oh Davina
oh so I talked about this in the serial
exit Davina is a way of reading and it's
it's it's it's a it's a practice now
I've been doing I guess for about a year
and I'm starting to get a sense of if
it's potential so when you read a text
and Lexi Oh Davina and this is to try
and get back to how we move to silent
reading and we moved
sort of propositional consumption is
what we're doing with reading was before
that people are reading communally and
they're reciting and the point of the
reading is to is to participate in an
aspiration for transformation right and
so what you do in Alexio Divina is you
take a text and then you you you you
read it aloud and then you basically go
into something like a meditative state
in which you're trying the way I
understand you're trying to let it
resonate with you that's what the
tradition talks about for me what I do
is I I try and enact it I try and I try
I try and do the reverse of excitation I
try to take this abstract thing right
and then the way it the way it's being
expressed metaphorically and reverse it
and actually embody it so the dow is is
like a well that's used but never used
up well what would what did we like to
actually be in that situation engage
that machinery really need it resonate
with you I've just done Tai Chi Chuan
I'm reading this and then I call up the
imagery you know uh you know and you can
almost feel it right you can feel
yourself like you know the thirst
there's the well I can go to it and
there's this inexhaustible nough stew it
and I it's you know okay and then I'm
feeling that and then you do this thing
when you try and embody it to the point
where it can start to challenge you to
transformation and then you often offer
any if you were like if you're a
Christian you would offer a prayer
before and then a prayer afterwards if
you're not a Christian like because this
is also a Neoplatonic practice
independent then what you do is okay
what am i committing to like what's
coming out of this there's an expression
of gratitude and commitment and so what
you do so you can see how it's it's it's
cut its again it's got aspects of the
dialectic because what you're trying to
get is is very much like what you're
getting encircling you're trying to get
a sense of of a presence between you and
the text that's emerging and calling you
forth there's a sense of being called Oh
of harkening as guys sense talk says
right so you're harkening to the words
not just reading the words and so lectio
do Lexi Oh Davina is something I've been
practicing
I want to and like I said part of our
one-hour explorers how does that right
come in to cause it integrate with what
we've been talking about under my term
dialectic so where I'll be personally is
I want to how are all these things going
to gel because whenever I take up a new
practice right it's not clear to me how
the ecology is going to reconfigure
around it and that's and like I said I
want to see and I want to help to try
and create it what does it look like
well as you said we're we're doing
content and not just or I said where the
recursive 'ti is about exemplification
and not just coming into the present
moment right all of that where I want
whether I see this series doing is I'm
hoping I'm hoping I can do with after
Socrates what people have said to me
that I did with awakening that I give a
vocabulary and a grammar for helping
people tap into this Kairos that we were
talking about that's what I see for
myself personally and that's what I'd
like to see the series doing like
interpersonally hmm yeah I guess what
I'd say as well is that what what where
is the where is the interaction point
between this which can be a little bit
kind of abstract or a little bit
intellectual and the mainstream and for
me that feels like it's around
impossible conversations is around
difficult conversations becoming
self-aware to how we are in conversation
seems to be there's been a few books out
recently peter Bogosian and James
Lindsay wrote having possible
conversations there's another couple of
books coming out that I'm aware of
around the same thing like how do you
have difficult conversations and the
only way and that was actually one of my
criticisms of their book is that it
didn't really go into the psychological
and into the interpersonal anywhere near
enough it was more about kind of
conversational techniques rather than
becoming sort of deeply deeply aware of
what we're bringing and what we're
what's happening to us when we're in
dialogue with others but that feels
absolutely essential as a kind of way
through or a way of kind of diffusing
some of the worst aspects of the of the
kind of polarization and the
the the culture wars that were that
we're seeing is becoming much more aware
of what we're bringing in what we're how
we are in conversation I agree with that
I mean part of part of what I'm doing in
in preparations I'm going through a lot
of the literature you referred to and
like verbal Aikido and you know you know
and nonviolent communication and trying
to understand all of that
and and I do agree with you that part of
what we have to facilitate is impossible
conversations but there's different
kinds of impossible conversations
there's impossible conversations because
we come in with different commitments
and values right and I understand that
and I acknowledge that we need to bring
something like dialectic to bear on that
but there's also other kinds of
impossible conversations where as we're
here and how do we get there it was like
what I talked about when you know when
there's a some episodes in the series
where I talk about that Gnostic sense of
being entrapped in a world and you could
you don't know how to get oh you want to
be there the kind of thing that people
experience in therapy when they're stuck
and it's important I shouldn't be doing
this anymore but they keep and they're
stuck and it's kind of an impossibility
for them is how do I get over there and
part of what happens in therapy is
another kind of impossible conversation
where it's not that these people are
coming in because they have conflicting
values it's like we're here and we're
stuck and how do we get there and I
think that's another important part
another important kind of impossible
conversation we need to learn how to
have because we have to get to somewhere
else than where we are part of it's
going to be what you said part of it is
like okay when we come in we've got us
somehow it reminds me of like the two
parts of platonic and Hana Gargan we've
got to reduce the interpersonal conflict
in some you know some way that's
affording that that that right that
didn't reassures the functionality but
we also have to learn how to take that
and get to somewhere that we're not
currently at and that's another kind of
impossible conversation and I'm really
interested in in that one a lot because
again you see both of those in the
Platonic dialogue you see Socrates
wrestling with people who are coming in
with all these you know for lack of a
better term political and often
self-serving agendas and but you also
see the other thing it's like we need to
get there
as human beings from here and we're
stuck and how do we get there so I wanna
I want to dress both of those kinds of
impossible conversations John thank you
very much thank you very much David
rebel wisdom is a new sense making
platform bringing together the most
rebellious and inspiring thinkers from
around the world if you're enjoying our
content then you can help us make more
by becoming a subscriber which will give
you access to a load of exclusive films
also you can then join our group zoom
calls to discuss the ideas in the films
and you can send us ideas for questions
for upcoming interviews and if you're a
regular viewer you'll know we talk a lot
about the value of embodying or actually
living out the ideas that we talk about
so that's why we run regular events in
London check out the links on the
website for more and hope to see you
soon
you